[Music]
the CDC recommends everyone over the age
of 6 months get a routine annual flu
shot every year unless you have some
sort of cont indication such as an
allergy to any of the components they
recommend trying to get it by the end of
October but maybe beneficial even
December or later how effective are flu
vaccines it depends on the year but
typically it reduces the risk of getting
the flu by about 40 to 50% so in healthy
adults we can say with moderate
certainty we can decrease the risk of
getting it from like you know 2% each
year down to just under 1% among older
adults you may get a similar relative
risk reduction but the Baseline risk is
higher and the consequences greater so
the absolute benefits are greater too in
kids flu vaccines really shine a high
certainty of evidence of substantial
drop in Risk but you know even in this
kind of best case scenario with
vaccination there's still a risk so what
else can we do each year Americans
experience millions of cases of
influenza and hundreds of millions of
cold what about Elderberry supplements
in a test tube Elderberry extracts can
inhibit pathogens including the flu
virus and in a Petri dish it can rev up
the production of flu fighting molecules
from Human immune system cells like
tumor necrosis Factor as much as nearly
45 fold and Elderberry juice can help
mice fight off the flu bow what about
actual people the first clinical trial
was published back in the 90s a
doubleblind randomized placebo control
trial to treat Fu like symptoms and odds
for improvement before the fifth day in
the treated group were more than 20
times the odds in the control group two
subsequent doubleblind randomized
Placebo control trials showed similar
accelerated healing in the Elderberry
groups this is the study I was excited
to see Elderberry supplementation for
cold symptoms in air Travelers given my
200 City book tour a randomized double
blind cable control clinical trial of
312 economy class passengers and while
taking Elderberry didn't seem to prevent
people from coming down with cold
symptoms the duration and severity of
symptoms in those that did get a cold
seem to have been lessened suffering on
average about 5 days instead of seven a
similar started using the herb eonia
found a lessening of symptom scores that
was of only borderline statistical
significance but if you compile all such
studies together even though most of the
individual trials didn't find
statistically significant improvements
put them together there may be about a
20% decreased cold incidents uh though
there is a concern about selective
reporting and publication bias meaning a
bunch of findings and entire studies
seem to be Mia suggesting Maybe negative
studies were quietly sheld so really
really not sure about eonia but all the
Elderberry studies seem to have positive
results suggesting Elderberry
supplementation provides an effective
treatment option when more serious
treatment isn't needed this conclusion
came from some with parent conflicts of
interest though in fact each of the four
Elderberry studies were funded by the
Elderberry product companies themselves
any other berries that might help or
random Placebo controlled Interventional
study funded predictably by Ocean Spray
found that the Gamma Delta tea cells of
those drinking a low calorie cranberry
juice beverage for 10 weeks appear to be
proliferating at nearly fivefold the
rate uh these immune cells are serve as
like a first line of defense though they
didn't get fewer colds but they did seem
to suffer less but not enough to
actually prevent days Miss from work or
an impairment of their activities but at
least you know cranberries have never
been reported to cause pancreatitis some
guy taking elderberry extract not only
suffered an attack of acute pancreatitis
a sudden painful inflammation of the
pancreas it went away when he stopped it
and then reappeared again years later
when he started taking it again which
suggests a cause and effect why take
Elderberry extracts though when you can
just eat the elderberries themselves
well cooked are fine but consuming raw
elderberries can cause you to PUK your
guts out oh now you tell me I uh found
out the hard way is I explained in an
answer to the question what was the
worst day of my life in my how not to
die London re
interview uh it turns out Elderberry
fruit form cyanide such that eight
people had to be medevaced out after
someone brought freshly squeezed
Elderberry juice to a gathering
[Music]